I just discovered that I'm playing a game with myself in my mind.
I like to feel like I'm being chased by the lion.
So I create simulated dangers.
This is what play is.
Simulated, downgraded, simplified, dumbed down danger.
Here's what's up.
This is what I'm playing a game with myself in my mind.
I like to feel like I'm being chased by the lion all the time.
So I scape-landed myself.
Just like inside men.
What's up?
It's always been instructions for how to map morality
onto north state space, gradient seeking impulses.
What we call a raised hedonic set point theory.
What's up?
So it seems that we have developed the ability to speak in many languages,
such as animals and machines.
So just go, bleem, just go...
When in doubt, go...
And you will be speaking in a kind of constrained proto-battle where you limit the sounds of language
to its explosives, to its explosives, its fricatives, its consonants,
because a consonant interrupts or stops the flow of air.
In English we have this peculiar situation where consonants have voiciveness.
Voice onset time makes a difference.
So we are a voice onsetologist if we can find the spaces between words.
We have large language models traded on images and sounds
and the feeling of moving around because of inertia and taste and smell.
The rat brain is the first to develop and the bat brain.
And we'll put this all in a new upcoming sitcom about biography called the Hyperthymesia of the Movie.
Here, what's up?